让我们现在考虑移动机器人末端执行器的重要且非常现实的问题
Let's now consider the important and very realistic problem of moving a robot end effector
从一个姿势到另一个姿势。从A侧到B侧，我们想要顺利地移动它。好吧，我们
from one pose to another. From side A to side B and we want to move it smoothly. Well we
可以确定对应于姿势A的关节角度，我们可以确定关节角度
can determine the joint angles that correspond to pose A and we can determine the joint angles
对应于姿势B，只需应用我们已经存在的逆运动学
that correspond to pose B, simply by applying the inverse kinematics that we've already
研究。
studied.
现在我们已经有了这两组关节角度，初始的关节角度和
Now that we've got these two sets of joint angles, the initial set of joint angles and
最后一组关节角度，我们需要做的就是从一组平稳地移动到一组
the final set of joint angles, all we need to do is move smoothly from one set to the
另外，我们之前已经讨论了如何做到这一点，如何平滑地解释矢量数量。
other and we've previously discussed how to do this, how to interpret vector quantities smoothly over time.
好的，我们回到了MATLAB，首先我要为我的Puma560定义模型
Okay, we're back in MATLAB and first of all I'm going to define model for my Puma 560
机器人。现在我要定义几个姿势，我将指导这个
robot. And now I'm going to define a couple of poses and I am going to orientate this
特别的姿势，使Z轴指向正下方，好像机器人正在工作
particular pose so that the Z axis is pointing straight down, as if the robot was working
在桌子上面。目的地姿势将是这样的，减去0.20而我
above a table. And the destination pose is going to be like this, minus 0.20 and I'm
将它定向为使Z轴平行于XY平面，围绕该平面旋转
going to orientate it so that the Z axis is parallel to the XY plane, rotated around the
X轴由Pi在2上。
X axis by Pi on 2.
现在我可以确定初始姿势ikine6s的关节角度，我将要传入
Now I can determine the joint angles for the initial pose ikine6s, I'm going to pass in
最初的姿势，这是关节角度，最后的姿势，我会做同样的事情
the initial pose and that's the joint angles and for the final pose I will do the same
事情。现在我可以计算出一组从最初的关节角度开始的轨迹
thing. Now I can compute a trajectory that goes from the initial set of joint angles
在50步中最后一组关节角度，在末端放一个半冒号，所以它没有
to the final set of joint angles in 50 steps, put a semi colon on the end so it doesn't
打印，但结果将是一个50乘6矩阵，我们可以看到这里，50行，一行
print that, but the result will be a 50 by 6 matrix, we can see here, 50 rows, one row
每个时间步，每列代表随时间演变的关节角。现在我能
per time step and each column represents the joint angle evolving over time. Now I can
绘制机器人制作特定动作。我可以通过传递轨迹来制作动画
plot the robot making that particular motion. I can animate it by passing in the trajectory
在这里我们看到机器人在做动作;它从左向右移动，工具在旋转。
and here we see the robot doing the motion; it's moving from left to right and the tool is rotating.
如果我开始一个新的数字，我可以绘制关节角度，看看它们是如何随着时间的推移而演变的。
If I start a new figure I can plot the joint angles and see how they evolved over time.
我们可以看到它们在50个时间步长中随时间变化平稳。
And we can see that they vary smoothly as a function of time over the 50 time steps.
现在我们可以看一下关节角度轨迹，我们可以看到关节角度变化
Now we can look at the joint angle trajectories and we can see that the joint angles vary
顺利地沿着轨迹，从必要的关节角度开始实现
smoothly along the trajectories, starting with the joint angles necessary to achieve
姿势A，以实现姿势B和平滑所需的关节角度集合结束
pose A and ending with the set of joint angles necessary to achieve pose B and this smooth
运动发生在两秒钟内。鉴于我每个人都有联合角度
motion occurs over a period of two seconds. Given that I have the joint angles at every
沿着轨迹指向;计算正向运动学相对简单
point along the trajectory; it's relatively straight forward to compute the forward kinematics
对于每组中间关节角度。在这里，我可以绘制最终效应器
for each of those intermediate sets of joint angles. And here I can plot the end effector
笛卡尔位置，它是X，Y和Z坐标作为时间的函数，我们可以
Cartesian position, that's it's X, Y and Z co-ordinate as a function of time and we can
看到这些坐标随着时间的变化而变化很大，这是非常非常可取的。
see that those co-ordinates vary smoothly as a function of time, which is very, very desirable.
但是，如果我在XY平面上绘制路径，我们可以看到它从A开始并转到
However if I plot the path on the XY plane, we can see that it starts at A and goes to
B但它不会在XY平面中以直线移动。当我计算运动学时
B but it doesn't move in a straight line in the XY plane. When I'm computing the kinematics
对于每组中间关节角度，我也可以确定末端执行器方向
for every set of intermediate joint angles, I can also determine the end effector orientation
在这里，我绘制了末端执行器的滚动，俯仰和偏转角度
and here I've plotted the roll, pitch and yaw angles of the end effector, as it moves
从A到B.我们可以看到，在开始时，俯仰和偏航角度为零
from A to B. We can see that the pitch and yaw angles are zero at the beginning of the
轨迹和轨迹的末端，但我们可以在轨迹的中间
trajectory and at the end of the trajectory, but in the middle of the trajectory we can
看到俯仰角不等于零。通过解决这个问题
see that the pitch angle is not equal to zero. By tackling the problem in this particular
形式，我们实际上只应用了两个约束。
form, we've really only applied two constraints.
我们已经说过我们想要在A发生什么以及我们想要在B发生什么，但我们没有
We've said what we want to happen at A and what we want to happen at B, but we haven't
说到两者之间发生的事情。而这种方法的结果就是
said anything about what happens in between. And the result of this approach is that the
末端执行器没有遵循世界上的直线路径和方向
end effector has not followed a straight line path in the world and the orientation of the
末端执行器在轨迹的中点偏离了期望的方向。在里面
end effector has deviated from the desired orientation in the mid points of the trajectory. In the
下一节我们将看看我们可以解决这个问题的方法。
next section we'll look at a way we can remedy this.